Jordan R. Villarreal

PROFESSIONAL OBJEECTIVE

Dedicated networking and technology enthusiast with 20+ years of field experience looking to transition to a pre/post sales engineering role. Socially savvy and effective communicator who is accustomed to using vast knowledge of networking technologies and adapting them to relatable concepts.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

PANDUIT CORPORATION

04/2018-PRESENT

SENIOR NETWORK ENGINEER

Hands on lead Network Engineer of Panduit's global engineering group. Working in an agile environment overseeing their global data networks. Responsible for evaluating, testing, and setting direction for network technologies. Participating in annual budget justification, creation, and dispursement. Active participant in disaster recovery planning and testing. Responsible for creating and driving global configuration standards. Interfacing with business units outside IT to help design and implement systems to support business changes. Participating engineer in all aspects of day-to-day operations.

SELECT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Implemented two new data centers using ACI
- Actively deploying ISE for new guest portal and wired/wireless NAC initiative
- Reduced budget creation time from a month long process to a two day process
- Worked with warehouse group to improve network to assist in streamlining shipping operations
- Worked with manufacturing groups to implement robotic automation to enhance employee workflow

COMMUNITY FOUNDATION OF NORTHWEST INDIANA, EAST CHICAGO, IN

10/2015-04/2018

TECHNOLOGY EVANGILIST/NETWORK ENGINEER II

Selected by CIO to operate as the overall IT team's "Technology Evangelist," continuously researching, recommending, and implementing new tools and technologies to improve overall operations within the department. Active participant in security committee where relevant topics are discussed, products evaluated, events responded to, and measures taken to enhance organizational IT security. Maintained network, spanning 80+ sites, over various WAN technologies. Deployed Meraki routers/switches along side traditional routers/switches. Utilized OSPF, EIGRP, RIPv2, and BGP routing protocols. Developed, implemented, and supported network standards, policies, and procedures. Monitored network using combination of packaged and open-source utilities such a, Nagios, Cricket, NetDisco, and others.

SELECT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Vetted, selected, and implemented new video conferencing platform to be used organization-wide
- Implemented 4 node Cisco ISE deployment to be utilized across wired and wireless networks
- Improved technican workfly by evaluating and integrating NetScout LinkRunner/Sprinter devices alongside link-live services
- Evaluated on-call alerting improvement applications (PagerDuty/VictorOps) and actively integrating VictorOps for PoC

NATIONAL COUNCIL OF STATE BOARDS OF NURSING, CHICAGO, IL

3/2012-10/2015

SENIOR SYSTEMS ENGINEER

Managed workloads for a group of dedicated, remote system engineers who assist in monitoring, maintaining, and configuring company owned devices and technologies. Delegating tasks, directing projects, and aligning internal resources to achieve desired outcomes for the group. Working to establish and maintain vendor relationships. Organizing SmartNET renewals. Managing external consultants through vetting process to completion of projects. Serving as primary lead for maintaining two data

centers (local and co-lo). Managing, monitoring, and maintaining Cisco (Nexus and IOS) switching, routing, firewall, IDS/IPS content filters, UCS, telephony, F5 load balancers, Steelhead traffic accelerators. Utilized OSPF, EIGRP, and BGP routing protocols. Rapidly designed protype environments for testing. Active participant in penetration scans, remediation plans, and implementing developed plans. Developed, implemented, and supported network standards, policies, and procedures. Maintained internal knowledge bases, wikis, and other internal knowledge warehouses. Monitoring network using combination of packaged and open-source utilities such as SolarWinds products, Splunk, Scrutinizer, Cacti, RANCID, and others. Participating in rotating on-call schedule. Served as backup member for server team.

SELECT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Saved \$50,000 in first year on annual remote support contracts
- Designed and implemented total network architecture overhaul; included a platform change from IOS to NX-OS
- Brokered asset exchange to save \$75,000 on infrastructure overhaul
- Resolved undiscovered network misconfiguration that was causing issues for an estimated 4 years span
- Completed work that enabled all employees to telecommute in the event of a total office closure

COMMUNITY FOUNDATION OF NORTHWEST INDIANA, EAST CHICAGO, IN NETWORK ENGINEER

11/2005-3/2012 2/2006 – 3/2012

Maintained network, spanning 20+ sites, over varios wired and wireless mediums. Supported Cisco Wireless LAN Controllers, Cisco Access Points, Cisco WCS, Cisco VPN Concentrator, PIX/ASA Firewall, Cisco and HP switches, Cisco routers (500+ total network devices), and Cisco Nexus. Utilized OSPF, EIGRP, RIPv2, and BGP routing protocols. Maintained internal knowledge bases, wikis, and other internal knowledge wharehouses. Coordinated and implemented installs of equipment for new and existing sites. Monitored network using combination of packaged and open-source utilities such as SolarWinds, Nagios, Cricket, What's Up Gold, and others. Participated in on-call schedule. Served as backup member for server team.

SELECT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Led upgrade of wireless network from autonomous wireless network to LWAPP.
- Lead responsible for \$500,000 upgrade project to wireless networking; project entailed estimating wireless coverage for 2.1 mil sq/ft of space, equipment procurement, contractor coordination, and all presentations for project
- Managed network restoration during disaster recovery tests at Sungard datacenter in Philadelphia
- Planned and managed organization's first multi-site live video conference system; used to save on inter-site travel to reduce unnecessary travel reimbursements
- Participated in full data-center reconstruction project involving full shutdown of all systems, reorganizing racks, and implementing Cisco Nexus end of row/top of rack design
- Led initiative driven by new Health Information System to visit, document, recommend, and implement upgrades for new and existing clinics in order to ensure a high level of customer satisfaction for new Epic Systems applications

DESKTOP NETWORK ANALYST I

11/2005 - 2/2006

Maintained desktop computers, laptops, printers, PDAs, and other end user equipment. Installed new computers and software, troubleshot software, and supported customer phone calls.

CHICAGO FAMILY HEALTH CARE, CHICAGO, IL

9/2004 – 11/2005

NETWORK ADMINISTRATOR

Single-handedly maintained network and computers across 3 small clinics. Utilized T1 connections heavily for internal and external connectivity. Maintained all desktop, printers, and PDAs within the environment. Installed and maintained Windows 2000/2003 servers for established domain. Acted as technology advisor for HIPAA committee and participated in policy drafting for necessary documentation.

SELECT ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Played integral role in selecting and installing new practice management software
- Established Microsoft Windows Controlled Domain
- Migrated users off individual dial up accounts to a centralized internet connection
- Implemented first help desk system for users to log requests for support

Intratech Computer/Networking Services Hammond, IN 6/2002 – 9/2004

COMPUTER TECHNICIAN/NETWORK INSTALLER

EDIGITALWORKS COMPUTER SERVICES HIGHLAND, IN 4/2001 – 6/2002

COMPUTER TECHNICIAN

PERSONAL SKILLS

- Able to clearly communicate concepts written and orally to individuals at varying technical levels
- Confidence in presenting information to, and being questioned by, groups of people
- Ability to analyze and solve problems independently or as part of a group
- Patience in dealing with users of differing abilities and from different cultures
- Organizational and supervisory skills

SOCIAL PRESENCE

- Content creator/writer on "The Art of Network Engineering" podcast
 - https://artofnetworkengineering.com
- Maintains active, networking centric, Twitter and YouTube presence
 - o https://twitter.com/SystemMTUOne
 - o https://www.youtube.com/c/SystemMTUOne/
- Regularly maintained LinkedIn profile
 - o https://www.linkedin.com/in/jordanvillarreal/

EDUCATION & TRAINING

BS IN SYSTEMS AND NETWORKING PURDUE UNIVERSITY HAMMOND, IN MAY 2012

- Semester Honors: SP04, FA04, SP05, FA05, FA06, SP07, FA07, FA08, SP09, FA09, SP10, SP11, FA11
- Dean's List: FA04, SP05, FA05, SP07, FA07, SP08, FA08, SP09, FA09, SP10, SP11, FA11
- Outstanding Student: SP06, SP10

VARIOUS COURSES VARIOUS PARTNERS IN PERSON/REMOTE 2008-2021

Course topics included wireless network design, Cisco CCNP ROUTE & SWITCH, VMWare VCP 5.1,
Cisco Firewall Design, ACI, QoS, ICOMM, CISSP preparation, SISE, ACI Operations & Troubleshooting

CERTIFICATES

Cisco

- CCNA
- CCNP Enterprise

VMWARE

VCP 5.1 (Previously held)